# **Utkarsh Ranjan**

(914)-267-5306

uranjan@ucsd.edu

in linkedin.com/in/utkarsh

Utkarsh

ranjanutkarsh.github.io

#### PERSONAL PROFILE

Graduate student at The University of California San Diego pursuing my masters at the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering specializing in Machine Learning and Data Science (MLDS). Zealous about software engineering with 3 years of experience specializing in machine learning, python development, data analytics. Primarily, looking for Machine Learning/Data Engineer/Python Developer roles.

## **EDUCATION**

### University of California - San Diego, California | US

Sep. 2022 – Present

M.S. in Electrical&Computer Engineering. (Major. Machine Learning and Data Science)

# Indian Institute of Technology (Banaras Hindu University), Varanasi | IN

B. Tech. in Electrical Engineering

Jul. 2015 - May 2019

GPA: 8.6 / 10

## **SKILLS**

Languages: Python, R, SQL, Java, C++

Big Data: PySpark, Hadoop, Map Reduce, AWS

Machine Learning: PyTorch, Pandas, Numpy, scikit-learn, Spacy, TensorFlow, Spark NLP

Technologies/Dev Tools: MongoDB, Tableau, Git, Power BI

#### **EXPERIENCE**

**Gartner,Inc** Jun. 2019 – Jun. 2022

Data Science Associate | Services - Data Science Team

Gurgaon, IN

#### IRIS: Recommendation System | PySpark, AWS, SparkNLP, Scikit-learn, Pandas, Neo4j, Git

- Developed Python based recommendation system to suggest actions for clients based on their digital footprints.
- Created graph embedding for clients using Neo4j to train models using activity history of peer connections

# GPR - IVR Survey: Comment Classification | SparkNLP, Scikit-learn, Pandas

- Developed a text classifier to mine the root causes of dissatisfaction from client feedback. Reached an F1- Score of 75% for determining action areas for corresponding business units
- Brought down the time spent from 2 weeks to 15 minutes for classifying client comments by creating a classification model using BERT
- Deployed trained scikit-learn ML models for spam classifier, entity recognition use-cases over PySpark real time ML pipeline using Natural Language Processing models.

#### SIVR: Creating a parameter to score client's engagement | Pandas, MongoDB

- Created a performance metric : SIVR using multivariate analysis on client engagement data to calculate the quality of value interaction with clients
- Spearheaded the development of an automated mailing system for service executives to ensure swift issue resolution and tracking

Gartner,Inc May. 2018 – Jul. 2018

Summer Intern | Services - Data Science Team

Gurgaon, IN

- Trained and test various supervised algorithms like Random Forest, Naïve Bayes and SVM using TF- IDF feature vectors to create a new FILTER in the tool achieved a **classification accuracy of 83%**
- Brought down the time spent from 15 hours per week to 2 hours by automating the process of report generation using python for efficient client service

## **Indian Institute of Space Science and Technology**

May. 2017 – Jul. 2017

Summer Intern | Department of Mathematics

Trivandrum, IN

- Developed a framework to capture the meaning of an unknown word by leveraging its root word and suffix through word embedding.
- Implemented Markov Chain Monte Carlo on UC Irvine Machine Learning Repository to achieve a macro- average precision of 91% over 11 classes.